# **ANUP KURIAKOSE**

Mobile: +61 470 582 683 5 Koonunga Crescent Home No: +61 3 9404 4452 South Morang

Email: joseph.anupsa@gmail.com Victoria
Visa: Permanent Resident of Australia 3752

Nationality: South African Date of Birth: 17 May 1980

# 1) Career Objective

To contribute significantly to an organization's profitability, efficiency and growth, while working in any of the following fields:

- Environmental Engineering
- Quality Engineering
- Project Management

## 2) Profile

I have more than seven years of experience working for *Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd*, which is one of the most successful Motor Manufacturing companies in the world.

During this period I was fortunate to work in many different fields of Engineering and Project Management, such as *Energy Engineering*, *Process Engineering* and *Quality Engineering*. In the same period I have also had the privilege of serving as a "*Manager*" in a department that deals with "Systems and Reporting".

I am an honest and hard working professional, who has a passion to be of service and "Continuously Improve" on existing standards and methods.

# 3) Career Summary

May 2012 – Jan 2013 Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)

Manager: SHE Systems and Reporting

December 2010 – April 2012 Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)

**Energy Engineer** 

April 2006 – November 2010 Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)

**Quality Engineer** 

January 2006 – March 2006 Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)

**Process Engineer** 

January 2004 – December 2005 Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)

**Engineering Management Trainee** 

## 4) Languages / Skills

Malayalam Mother Tongue

English Fluent Afrikaans Intermediate

Computer Skills (Basic) Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Internet

**Computer Programming Skills** 

(Advanced) Visual Basic, Matlab, C and C++

## 5) Professional Experience

December 2010 – April 2012 Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)

**Energy Engineer** 

Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd is the only manufacturer of Toyota Motor Cars in the African Continent. TSAM is a large company that employs over 7000 people and manufactures various Toyota Vehicles such as the "Toyota Corolla" and "Toyota Hilux". These vehicles are sold both within Africa and also exported to other parts of the world such as Europe and South America. TSAM is currently the market leader in the South African Motor Industry Sector and this is a position it has held in the country for more than 30 years.

## Key responsibilities:

- Identify and initiate Energy Efficiency projects in TSAM.
- Develop Energy Efficient solutions.
- Project Management of Energy Efficiency Projects.
- Measurement of results after implementation of Energy Efficiency projects.
- Commissioning of Energy Efficiency Projects after completion.
- Continuous Measurement and monitoring of Energy consumption levels in TSAM.
- Continuously Report Energy Consumption results to Areas in TSAM.
- Presentation of Energy Efficiency activities to Senior Executive Management of TSAM.
- Implementation of ISO 50001 Energy Management System.

## Key achievements:

- Reduced overall 2011 Energy Consumption in all Non-production Areas of TSAM by 25%.
- Reduced Sunday 2011 Energy Consumption in all Non-production Areas of TSAM by 28%.
- Reduced 2011 Air-conditioner Energy Consumption in Administration areas by 22% per annum.
- Installed lighting controls in all Main Ablution Areas of TSAM, to reduce their Energy usage by 7028 kWh/month.
- Reduced monthly Energy usage in Vehicle "Test Track" Area by 26%.

## April 2012 – January 2013

Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa) Manager: SHE Systems and Reporting

"SHE" division (Safety, Health and Environmental) within TSAM (Toyota SA Motors) is the division that manages and cordinates all the Safety, Health and Environmental issues of TSAM.

#### Key responsibilities:

- Electricity and Water Meter calibration and maintenance Management.
- Waste Scale Management.
- Programming and Streamlining of SHE information database.
- Managing and Co-ordinating ISO 14001, ISO 50001 and ISO 9001 Systems in SHE division.
- Manager of "Information and Data capturing team".
- Audit Management of ISO 14001, ISO 50001 and ISO 9001.

## Key achievements:

- Reprogrammed SHE database and Reports, to reduce total capturing of information by 79 %.
  - Zero findings on ISO 14001 documentation during External Audit.

## April 2006 – December 2010

Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa)
Quality Engineer (Assembly Division)

"Assembly" division within TSAM (Toyota SA Motors) is the division that deals with the final stage of Manufacturing, of the Toyota Motor Vehicle. Here the vehicles go through the process of having the various motor vehicle parts assembled onto it. This area of manufacturing has 2 main production lines and builds close to 650 Toyota vehicles in a day. The models built on these lines are the "Toyota Corolla", "Toyota Hilux" and "Toyota Fortuner" models. These vehicles are sold both within Africa and also exported to other parts of the world such as Europe and South America.

## Key responsibilities:

- Internal and External Quality Problems' Lead Investigator and Coordinator for the Assembly Division of TSAM.
- Compiling and controlling of Internal and Field Quality Problem investigation reports.
- Presentation and Feedback on Quality Problem Investigations to Senior Management.
- Design and Maintenance of Assembly Hall Quality Problems' database.
- Project Management of Quality Engineering Projects.

## Key achievements:

- Reduced External Quality problems in Assembly Division of TSAM by 26% between 2007 and 2011.
- Successful design and implementation of Quality Problems' Database.
- Successful implementation of Brake-fluid filling equipment using Vacuum Technology.

### January 2006 - March 2006

# Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa) Process Engineer (Weld Division)

"Weld" division within TSAM (Toyota SA Motors) is the division that deals with building the "Body" of the Toyota Motor Vehicle. The "Weld" division receives pressed (Steel) body panels from the "Press Plant" of TSAM. Here these different body panels go through various welding processes (such as Spot welding and CO2 welding) to be welded together to make the body of a Toyota Motor car. This area of manufacturing has 2 main production lines and builds close to 650 Toyota vehicles in a day. The models built on these lines are the "Toyota Corolla", "Toyota Hilux" and "Toyota Fortuner" models. These vehicles are sold both within Africa and also exported to other parts of the world such as Europe and South America.

### Key responsibilities:

- Projects involving maintenance and improvement of Toyota Corolla Body Accuracy,
- Quality Problems Investigation,
- Design of various systems and processes to continuously improve quality.
- Weld Plant Sealer usage monitoring system project.

## Key achievements:

- Completed implementation of Weld Plant Sealer usage monitoring system and reduced Overall sealer usage by 33%.
- Improved Toyota Corolla Body accuracy from 91% to 96%.

## January 2004 – December 2005

Toyota SA Motors (Pty) Ltd, Durban (South Africa) Engineering Management Trainee (Weld Division)

Please refer to previous career description for explanation on "Weld" division.

## Key responsibilities:

- Projects involving maintenance and improvement of Hilux Body Accuracy,
- Quality problems investigation,
- Design of various systems and processes to continuously improve quality.
- Body Shop Sealer usage monitoring system project
- Gain an overall understanding of Production Systems involved in Toyota.

## Key achievements:

- Successful completion of the Engineering Management Trainee program.
- Achieving above 75% for all modules in the program.

# 6) Other Work Experience

Nov 2002 – Jan 2003 ARMSCOR (South Africa), Software Engineer, June 2000 - July 2000

University of Natal, Physics Department (South

Africa), Design Engineer,

7) Education

1998-2004 **Bsc in Engineering (Electronic)** 

University of Natal, Durban (South Africa)

(Approved as a "Professional Engineer" qualification by

"Engineers Australia")

2006-2007 Post Graduate Diploma in Business Management

Management College of Southern Africa (South Africa)

# 8) Activities and Interests

Chairman of Body Corporate – Marina Mews Complex (Durban – South Africa) Reading books on Spirituality and Self Improvement. Mindfulness Meditation Sports: Action Cricket and Gym Full driving license

# 9) Referees

Please note that references are available upon request.